You have about two minutes to leave an impact on your audience. After that, you start to lose their attention.
So in those two minutes, you really need to convey your most important messages up front.
Don’t spend that time giving all your evidence and supporting arguments to get to your main point.
Start with your main point, and then layer in your supporting arguments and your evidence behind it.
We call this the pyramid principle. So if you think of a pyramid,
your most important point is up top, and that’s where you start. And then you layer in the supporting arguments and all the myriad of facts that underlie those, down at the bottom.
So let’s talk about what’s in the pyramid. At the top of the pyramid is your governing thought.
This is the key takeaway that you want people to hear. This is the thing that you communicate in the first two minutes.
The governing thought is essentially the answer to the question that you’re trying to answer, right? So if you’ve gone into a meeting and
either the CFO or the CEO or your manager has asked you to go away and think about: should we invest in the following technology? Should we expand into the following regions? How should we improve our sales force productivity?
Beneath that is another layer, which are your key line statements.
No more than three to five. If you have more than that, people start to get lost.
That’s really all people can handle or remember:
three to five key line statements that really compose your supporting argument.
And these are the key statements, essentially, that answer the question why or how.
Right, so you’ve made a governing thought: yes, we should invest in the following technology, because it will improve our productivity by 20%.
We should expand into the following geography because it’s a growing market and fits within our portfolio. The bottom layer
is comprised of your foundational facts. These are all the facts, all the pieces of information, that actually synthesize up into your key line statements, that then boil up into your governing thought.
An example: where you’re driving towards a large-scale organizational change,
the governing thought at the top of your pyramid would be what you’re trying to create. What are you trying to build as a result of this change journey you’re embarking on?
The supporting arguments underneath would be the themes of what you’re doing to get there.
And then the foundational arguments at the bottom would be lists of initiatives and specific actions that you’re taking to drive that change.